Guide to the Walter Crane Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Walter Crane Collection
1876-1915
GEN MSS 1418
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.79
4 boxes
Crane, Walter, 1845-1915
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 1956-2016. For more information, see the finding aid.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1876-1915. II. Artwork and Writings, 1878-1909.
Walter Crane (1845-1915)
Walter Crane (1845-1915), English author and illustrator best known for his work in children's literature. Among the most important illustrators of the nineteenth century, Crane was also a painter, essayist, and decorative artist who created designs for wallpapers, tiles, printed textiles, posters, stained glass, embroideries, and pottery. His formal education consisted of an apprenticeship served with the wood engraver and illustrator W. J. Linton from 1858 to 1862; later he was a founder of The Art-Workers' Guild (1884) and a founder and first president of The Arts and Crafts Exhibition Society (1888).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains original sketches, drawings, autograph manuscripts, and autograph letters, signed, by the English illustrator Walter Crane. Prominent are the original drawings for two of Crane's illustrated books, Queen Summer, or The Tourney of the Lily and the Rose (London: Cassell & Co., 1891) and A Floral Fantasy in an Old English Garden (New York and London: Harper and Bros., 1899). Correspondents include Kineton Parkes and Frederic Shields. Also present is a ceramic tile bearing an image by Crane, and his watercolor landscape titled "Swedish Twilight."
Artists -- Great Britain; Children's literature -- Illustrations; Illustration of books -- Great Britain; Illustrators -- Great Britain; Illustrations (layout features) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Sketchbooks -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Tile (material) -- United States -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Artists -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Illustrators -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915; Parkes, Kineton, 1865-1938; Shields, Frederic, 1833-1911
- Correspondence, 1876–1915; Series I; 0.42; 1 box
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - Begbie, Agnes Helen, 1909 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased from Paul C. Richards Autographs on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1964.
  - Bell, Mackenzie, 1895–1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Purchased on the Robert Metzdorf on the Naphtali Daggett Fund, 1957.
  - Bunce, John Thackray, 1890 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Mace Neufeld (Yale 1948) in honor of Mr. and Mrs. M. Katz, 1963.
  - Burnett, Brandon, 1892 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Removed from Renascence: a Book of Verse, by Walter Crane (BEIN J18 C851 891Rd); gift of Philip M. Neufeld, 1969.
  - Cobden-Sanderson, T. J. (Thomas James), 1897 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Purchased Charles A. Stonehill, Jr. on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1963.
  - Conway, William Martin, Sir, 1888–1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Catharine Tinker Patterson, 1958.
  - Deschamps, Charles, 1878–1881 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Gift of Mace Neufeld (Yale 1948) in honor of Mr. and Mrs. M. Katz, 1963; letter of April 4, 1881, gift of Donald C. Gallup (Yale 1934), 1986.
  - Fothergill, George Algernon, 1911, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letter from 1911 purchased from Charles Hamilton on the Edward Wells Southworth Fund, 1958; letter from 1915 purchased from W. R. Benjamin on the Plain Fund, 1957.
  - Gaskin, Mrs., 1876 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Purchased from Paul C. Richards Autographs on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1964.
  - Jones, T. E., 1898 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kirkwood, Mr., 1891 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Purchased from John Wilson on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1986.
  - Marzials, Theophilus, 1880 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Concerning their work on Pan-Pipes (London: G. Routledge and Sons, 1883).
    Gift of Donald C. Gallup (Yale 1934), 1986.
  - Mills, Mrs., 1911 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Concerning the death of Frederic Shields.
    Purchased on the William L. Phelps Fund, 1958.
  - The New Age (editor), 1907 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Inscribed at top: "Socialism and Art."
    Purchased from Howard S. Mott on the Douglas M. Moffat Fund, 1962.
  - Parkes, Kineton, 1889, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Concerning a proof of his poems; accompanied by an autograph poem, "Rondeau: Written Upon a Settle."
    Removed from Crane's Renascence (BEIN J18 C851 891Rc); gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Catharine Tinker Patterson, 1958.
  - Parkes, Kineton, 1901 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Purchased from Paul C. Richards Autographs on the Herman W. Liebert Book Fund, 1964.
  - Prang, Louis, 1891 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Purchased from Paul C. Richards Autographs on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1965.
  - Rersol, M. Balarsfy, 1900 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of Charles Frost, 1960.
  - Royal Institute of Painters in Water Colour (Great Britain), 1883 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Two letters to H. F. Phillips, secretary, concerning the cover of an exhibition catalogue.
  - Sandford, Herbert Bruce, 1889 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shields, Frederic, 1897–1903 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Concerning the decoration of the Chapel of the Ascension, Bayswater Road, London.
    Purchased on the William L. Phelps Fund, 1956. Letter of June 9, 1898, purchased from Paul Richards on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund, 1964.
  - Skeen, A. E., 1901 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sumner, Heywood, 1893 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Trist, John, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Valpy, Arthur Sutton, 1879 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Whelen, Frederick, 1911 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Requesting that his name be added to a telegram to Maxim Gorky.
  - Withers, Mr., 1912–1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Gift of Philip M. Neufeld in honor of George Alpert, 1961.
  - Unidentified recipients
    - To "Dear Sir", 1885 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - To "Dear Sir", 1889 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - To "Dear Sir", 1894 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Purchased from Brick Row Bookshop on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1966.
    - Christmas greeting card, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Printed card with autograph note on verso: On verso: "Beaumont Lodge. Xmas. 1890. Fridays. 4-6"
      Purchased from Collectors' Editions on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 2002.
    - To "Dear Madam", 1910 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Advising her that his early toy and picture books are being reissued.
      Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the Hubert Amer McGuire Memorial Fund, 1960
  - Autograph, 1907 October (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Source unknown.
- Artwork and Writings, 1878–1909; Series II; 3.05; 3 boxes
  - "Illusions", undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Autograph manuscript; 1 p.; poem published in his compilation Renascence.
    Purchased from William Reese Company (Bonhams sale, 2016 June 8, lot 87), on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
  - Folk and Fairy Tales, by Constance Burton Harrison (London: Ward and Downey, 1885) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Drawing for "The Story of the Moorish Dish"; ink and Chinese white on card. The book was issued in the United States as: Bric-a-Brac Stories (New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1885).
    Purchased from Charles on the William L. Phelps Fund, 1957
  - A Floral Fantasy in an Old English Garden (New York and London: Harper and Bros., 1899), 1898 (Box 2)
    Nineteen drawings in watercolor on paper for endpapers and for illustrations on pp. [1], [2], 6-7, 9, 11, 15, 17-18, 20, 22-26, 38, and 45; also, a drawing with crane and brushes, not used. The drawings are interleaved with the printed version, first edition, bound in green full levant morocco by Riviere & Son. Inscribed on verso of leaf 3: "Mary Frances Crane with the author's love, Dec. 31, 1898."
  - "Flood at Winterburg", 1890 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Ink on paper; titled and signed at lower right corner. Crane recounted his visit to Winterburg (Vimperk, Czech Republic), and the flood there on page 347 of his autobiography, An Artist's Reminiscences (1907).
    Purchased from William Reese Company (Bonhams sale, 2016 June 8, lot 87), on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund Fund, 2016.
  - "Fortune and the Boy" from The Baby's Own Aesop, circa 1892 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Transfer-printed, polychromed, glazed earthenware tile manufactured by the Wheeling Pottery Company, Wheeling, West Virginia.
    Purchased from Howard S. Mott, Inc., on the Hall Park McCullough Fund, 1963.
  - "On the Suppression of Free Speech in Chicago", 1886 June (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Autograph manuscript, signed; 1 p.
  - "Original sketch for modern walking dress", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Gouache and ink on illustration board; title from inscription by Crane on verso.
    Purchased from Walter Schatzki on the Elizabeth W. Manwaring Fund, 1969.
  - Queen Summer, or the Tourney of the Lily and the Rose (London: Cassell & Co., 1891) (Box 3)
    Twenty-seven drawings in black ink and watercolor on paper, inserted in printed large paper copy, first edition, rebound. Drawings are for front and back covers and for illustrations on pp. 1-2, 6, 12, 16-17, 20-26, 28-32, and 34-40; also, a preparatory drawing for illustration on p. 2, not used.
    Gift of Charles J. Rosenbloom (Yale 1920), 1972.
  - Sketchbooks, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Two notebooks with autograph notes, sketches and drawings made May 1, 6-7, 19, and July 4-5, 7, 1900. Contents include several drawings from nature at the Labour Day at the Crystal Palace (May 1, 1900); notes and drawings from his trip to Hungary; notes for his Line and Form (London: George Bell & Sons, 1900); and notes for his directorship of the Art Department at Reading College.
    Gift of Robert J. Barry, 1956.
  - "Swedish Twilight", 1909 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 42)
    Watercolor on paper mounted on board; signed lower left: "Walter Crane / 1909" with monogram. Inscribed by Crane on verso of mount: "No. 7 / Swedish Twilight / Walter Crane R. W. S. 13 Holland St. Kensington London W."
  - Travels with a Donkey in the Cévennes (London, C. K. Paul & Co., 1879), circa 1878 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Frontispiece drawing; ink, graphite, wash, and Chinese white on tracing paper, with a note from Lionel Crane authenticating the sketch.
    Removed from Travels with a Donkey in the Cevennes, by Robert Louis Stevenson (BEIN 1976 +147); scene described on page 61 of the volume; gift of Charles J. Rosenbloom (Yale 1920), 1970.